[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's Madhyamanika 125, Tantabhumi Sutta, and the reason we selected this particular one, it came up in the past, and it's a usual description of the gradual training that the Buddha would give.
[SPEAKER_00]: And whereby, when a person has become skilled in abandoning hindrances, then there would be, commonly, the description will continue by describing the first jhāna, second jhāna, third jhāna, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in this Manjuma 125, that part is different.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead of jhāna, the Buddha describes the four foundations of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're in place of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'll read out a bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having abandoned these five hindrances, imperfections of mind, of awareness, that awaken the discernment, he remains mindful of the body within the body, ardent, alert and mindful,
[SPEAKER_00]: Subduing greed and distress, joys and griefs in regard to the world, he remains mindful of feeling within feeling, mind within mind, and dhammas within dhammas, ardent, alert and mindful, subduing greed and distress in regard to the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, so the common standard description of satipaṭṭhāna, body within the body, feelings within feelings, mind within mind, and thoughts within thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: The main point there, it's, as we said in the past talks, is that, well, in order to be done rightly, it needs to be done for the right reasons, which means one needs to have a right view in order to understand what body within body actually is correctly, how to see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the reason why the satipaṭṭhānas are the reference points, it's because
[SPEAKER_00]: Generally, day-to-day experience is rooted in the sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I meant in the past when I kept saying like a centralized and whereby you put your sense of self first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, that's not something... it's on the level of choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not done as a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't choose to put yourself first by simply not having the right view,
[SPEAKER_00]: By, you know, acting out of desires, irritations, resistances, pressures, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of those acts put your assumed sense of self first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything else is second.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a subtle thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's easy to understand on that, like, a coarser level.
[SPEAKER_00]: But actually, the principle, it's very subtle to the point of the subtlest conceits, are these little perversions of what comes first, what you put first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in this sense, most common experience would be on the level of
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, things are for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things are happening to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasures are for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pains are against me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, it's me who is that center.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even when people practice the... try to practice their sense of mindfulness, they do that through that sense of me and through that sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the reason why satipaṭṭhānas are the direct way, as the Buddha said, that would result in the complete purification of beings, of the mind, of the of the kilesas and everything that's unwholesome, is because you get to undo that wrong order in these satipaṭṭhānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not body for me, body away from me,
[SPEAKER_00]: bodies, mind, all these other things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically, you see body within the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is no room for that sense of I am to take over and become the center of that experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, as I say, it's the right view for that is necessary, because if somebody is still not free from the fetter of attavāda,
[SPEAKER_00]: that assumed external sense of self, externally independent of this experience as a whole, you couldn't possibly conceive what it's meant by body within body.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you can have an idea of it, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the whole point of it is somebody who has seen the sense of self as within the experience as a whole, in the broadest terms,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, somebody who is free from atavāda, then all they need to do is use this one of these four reference points that would then keep sustaining that right order of putting that sense of I am and conceit that's still there to some extent, just putting it second.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how it fades.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it fades
[SPEAKER_00]: By not being maintained in that gratuitously, eh... sort of, eh... elevated position of... of... oh, this is the center of... of the experience and this... this... this person is... well, this sense of I am is in charge and so on and it's... it's like the... and things revolve around it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, seeing whichever way you look, you see body within the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or there is such and such feeling present
[SPEAKER_00]: Not for me, not in me, not against me.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just feeling within that feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, either way, wherever you look, you look at the right order, puts one of these four reference points, puts them first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, sense of self, of course, for somebody who is not fully enlightened, an arahant, will still linger there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But your point is not to, eh... intentionally try to get rid of that sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is to sustain the right order that prevents that sense of self from taking over and assuming that central position again.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, if the satipaṭṭhānas are done, sustained, as reference point, regardless of what experience you're going through, the right order is sustained, eh... regardless of what experience you're going through.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you are purifying yourself from the perversion of your own conceit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what it meant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, he contemplates body in the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: How?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, by contemplating repulsiveness of the body, subject to illness, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all these things that, basically, they would be freeing your mind from passion in regard to body, is on the level of seeing body correctly as not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Body as that which my sense of self depends upon, not other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, seeing body in the body, body within the body, which I really want to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the first paragraph describes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having abandoned the five hindrances, he remains mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to have surmounted the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sensual desire, ill will, sloth and torpor, doubt, restlessness and worry and doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, these are not
[SPEAKER_00]: These are not small things and they would require quite a degree of wisdom and that sort of right type of endurance of not acting out of those things until the mind has seen beyond them, until the mind has learned how to operate under them.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, once the mind gets used to that, those hindrances do not exercise as much power over the mind and then he remains seeing first is first, body in the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or feeling in the feeling, mind in the mind, and none of that is taken up in that centralized sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the important bit here.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why exactly it would lead to jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is not an accidental sort of mix up, to say like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then the Buddha gives a simile.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just as when the elephant tamer plants a large post in the ground,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the same way, these four foundations of mindfulness are bindings for the mindfulness of the disciple, of the noble one, and break him of his household habits, household memories, and resolves
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for the culmination of the right method, for the culmination of the right view, which means you need to have had right view in order for it to be brought to culmination.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, in the same way, these four foundations are bindings for the mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, these four reference points sustain the correct type of recollectedness, as we say, of that non-perverted order.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and again, I'm repeating this because people might end up expecting, okay, so if I'm rightly mindful, there is no sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is still conceit, there are still pressures, there are still desires, but if instead you're trying to... if instead of trying to engage with them directly, to...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll deal with this, and then I'll deal with this, and then I'll keep saying to myself, uh, anatta, anatta, anatta, and removing the sense of self, uh, you instead actually invest your effort in sustaining
[SPEAKER_00]: Thoughts within the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are dealing with the conceit.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are uprooting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by protecting the right order, the conceit is being extinguished, eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what a noble disciple would know, which is why, again, if, what the Buddha said, if the, in satipaṭṭhāna sutta, if he practices, like, you know, for seven days or, what, seven months or seven years, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: The outcome of it will have to happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, the purification cannot not happen, because it's
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having abandoned the five hindrances, he binds his mindfulness correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: The conceit is still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pressures are still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's exactly what it's meant by the simile.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the elephant's memories of the wilderness and fatigue and distraction are still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the tamer is not trying to calm the elephant whenever elephant is sort of acting out of its memories, or desires, or pressures.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: He just binds him to something that's seen as thing that can sustain that right order.
[SPEAKER_00]: He binds him to a post of body in the body, mind in mind, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that will calm all these wild tendencies in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the same for the monk who trains, or a person who trains.
[SPEAKER_00]: He binds
[SPEAKER_00]: His wild mind, his mind of conceit, that still tries to pressure him into perverting the order through greed, aversion, delusion, he binds it into this this right order, and by doing so, endures these pulls, because he knows, he has enough wisdom to see that through enduring these pulls, having being bound in the right order, these pressures and wild tendencies and household memories will fade away.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, he doesn't try to manage them.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has established the right order that has resulted in direct uprooting, eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, not overnight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, for somebody, maybe even overnight, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the Tathāgata trains him further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kammāṅga, remain contemplating body within the body, feeling within the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, remain referenced in the right order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Remain seeing the body in that decentralized sense, as a thing that endures there,
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of which you have all these precious pulls and sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of which you keep thinking you are the center.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of which your conceit keep taking all these are for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see all of that as second to the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whichever way you approach your experience, all you're gonna see is body within this body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, or this body within the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or feeling within the enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a feeling within me, feeling for me, feeling away from me, feeling against me, past feeling, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling is there within the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the pressures, all the conceits, all the self-centered kind of notions,
[SPEAKER_00]: are peripherally enduring, but you are not abandoning the gateway of the right order.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, remain contemplating body in the body, and the other references, and do not think any thoughts connected with the sense desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's always that thing that we keep mentioning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensuality, in a sense, has to be overcome, has to be understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't disappear on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it has to be overcome, sorry, through an
[SPEAKER_00]: They won't just disappear on account of, you know, experiencing peaceful pleasure or focusing practices and something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: They disappear when gratification, danger and escape is understood in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: They still might be harassing the mind that is rightly referenced, but the point is then to sustain that right reference, and then not give in to these harassing thoughts that would want to pervert your order and get you hooked on to thinking, well, basically, thinking that ugly is beautiful and the desire is that comes first and the satisfaction is there in the world through the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: Do not think any thoughts of connective desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, with stilling of thinking and pondering, he would then enter and remain, or he would remain having entered, in the second jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Joy, pleasure, born of composure, unification of the mind, free from thinking and pondering, internal assurance, internal confidence.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, with fading of the joy, he remains a quanimous, mindful alert, experiencing pleasure with the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, this part of the sutta then concludes by...
[SPEAKER_00]: By saying, having remained established in the right order of seeing body within the body, but do not think any thoughts connected with sensuality, and not not thinking any thoughts, doesn't mean like you prevent the thoughts from arising, means not welcoming, delighting, accepting any thoughts that are trying to pressure you.
[SPEAKER_00]: on account of or pressure you through sensuality, when you're correctly referenced in seeing body within the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any thoughts that are trying to pressure you, thoughts connected with pleasures, displeasures, and so on, you don't accept them, you don't welcome them, so you don't think them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they will still be buzzing around and trying to to pervert the order, as I said before, but
[SPEAKER_00]: Purification and refinement of the principle of mindfulness then results in jhāna, as the Buddha describes, when you start basically even noticing those little pressures of the little thoughts and not accepting them and welcoming them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the guard, the the gateway, becomes protected, even in regard to those those subtler, subtler pressures, that the mind is otherwise kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: you know, accepting, not noticing, acting out, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not accepting, not seeing, not accepting, not putting first, not centralizing your experience around those pressures, will then result in complete stilling internally of thinking and pondering,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the stilling of that rapture that's experienced in the body and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's important to just repeat that the point is to sustain the right order in face of pressures.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's pretty much the principle of the entire Satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in this sutta, the Buddha shows how that principle
[SPEAKER_00]: Taken to its fulfillment, whereby thoughts of sensuality, thoughts connected in regard to the body, and the pleasures of the body, and the joys of the body, and the disagreeability of the body, those thoughts are seen
[SPEAKER_00]: through the right order of body within the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, thoughts connected to the... with the body, thoughts concerned about the body, are now seen as bodily, so to speak, through the right order of seeing body within the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when somebody is established in the mindfulness of the body, thoughts connected to the body, thoughts about sensuality, could be still taken to some extent,
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is, no, by not taking them, by not delighting them, by not welcoming them, by not thinking them intentionally, they will be left there, sort of coming and going, peripherally, enduring, trying to pressure you, trying to assail you, trying to pervert their order, through making you take them up.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't take them up, you just see body within the body and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the subtlest, most pressing thoughts are seen now as second, as everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you start seeing them as first, means they have become centralized again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your conceit has perverted the order.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the practice of purification.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm perverting and then sustaining that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even to these subtle degrees.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter how personal those thoughts might be, how subtle, how fleeting, they're all seen, they all remain second.
[SPEAKER_00]: They all remain not taken up, not placed in this self-centered sense of experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, then the sutta continues on, just with standard description of if one has developed his mind in this manner,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what should be taken from this, is that one needs the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because without the right view, one will not know what the right endurance is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because one's endurance and everything else one does will be still rooted, without the right view, would still be rooted in craving, in trying to get rid of discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know what level you have to endure the things for the craving to cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by not knowing what level that is, you are acting out of craving and you're feeding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, once the person has the right view, knows what the... and has been practicing the gradual training, because this... this whole description, by the way, you cannot just take it and
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if somebody does this gradual training rightly, it will be highly unlikely they won't have a right view by then, by this time, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if one has taken the virtue rightly,
[SPEAKER_00]: is moderate, is bought full of his intentions, behind his actions, and use the pressure if acting out would imply that it's... would reveal that it's rooted in greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's... that's already sufficient self-transparency to start basically recognizing
[SPEAKER_00]: That sense of self can actually come second.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you can say that to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can imagine that you are not in control.
[SPEAKER_00]: But fundamentally, as the Buddha said, without that right view, a puthujjana would be seeing self with self.
[SPEAKER_00]: would be seeing self with not-self, would be seeing not-self with self.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he can't see not-self with not-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: He can't see body in the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: He can't see body with the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: He can't see feeling with the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: There has to be him involved in seeing it or referring to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having abandoned Atavāda, having abandoned that Gacchurju's assumption of the sense of self existing outside of this experience as a whole, as an independent owner-master of it, you can actually see body within the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: or body with the body, feeling in the feeling, because sense of self is redundant.
[SPEAKER_00]: That self-centered seer, the knower, or whatever else people call it, it's completely redundant, and it's a symptom of the problem of gratuitously perverting order, with the perversion being
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if that has been subdued through the gradual training, the reference point of body within the body
[SPEAKER_00]: Satipaṭṭhāna also says, will make that sense of self, that self-centered assumption, that the self has to be in the center, that it is for me, I am, and so on, will make that seen as utterly redundant and not necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, you just have to keep sustaining that knowledge and that recognition, and not carelessly give in to the old habit of putting yourself first, putting your sense of self first, through desires, ill-will and distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, seeing body in the body, in other way, or feeling in the feeling, in other way, means exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being able that with not-self, see not-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: With that which is clearly not mine,
[SPEAKER_00]: I see not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, nothing can be mine because this is the basis of experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is that reference point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even all this pressure that I might still be experiencing on account of traces of conceit that are around to make
[SPEAKER_00]: me take things as mine to make the me sort of accept, welcome, delight and put it first.
[SPEAKER_00]: I see even that as something that cannot be taken as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that can only be seen through a rightly established order, through a right reference.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you think you're seeing that directly, like, oh, this cannot be mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that experience is yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: That experience has been taken as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I said in the beginning, it's not a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't just intentionally choose to not take anything as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that intentional experience is taken, is yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you see that, regardless of the extent of sense of I am, regardless of the extent of the ownership, assumptions, and mind, and self-centeredness, all of that,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's within the enduring body here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's within the enduring feeling here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's indeed within the enduring state of mind here and now, or within the enduring thoughts, more specific, the context of your thoughts here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize, okay, so it doesn't matter how far it goes, how pressuring it is, it always is the second.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot become the first.
[SPEAKER_00]: The clearer, the firmer the knowledge of that is,
[SPEAKER_00]: The possibility of perverting that order ever again fades more and more.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly pretty much what it's meant by purification of the mind, purification of things that are unwholesome, purification of asavas, of the taints and all the different translations of it, means basically removal of the possibility of perverting the order ever again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if the order cannot be
[SPEAKER_00]: Perverted ever again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing that used to exist on account of perverted order can manifest ever again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Desire, anger, ill-will, sensuality, conceit, appropriation, ownership, distraction, delusion, avijjā.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the basis of it is removed through correct contemplation of body in the body, mind in the mind, feeling in the feeling, or thoughts in the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's about it.